<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe treatise, to prooue the necessitie and excellence of the vse of archerie. Abstracted out of ancient and moderne writers. By R:S. Perused, and allowed by aucthoritie</title>
            <author>R. S., fl. 1596.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1596</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11250</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21512</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116313</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851530</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851530</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16807</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11250)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16807)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 469:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe treatise, to prooue the necessitie and excellence of the vse of archerie. Abstracted out of ancient and moderne writers. By R:S. Perused, and allowed by aucthoritie</title>
                  <author>R. S., fl. 1596.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p. : ill. (woodcut)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Iohnes, at the Rose and Crowne; next aboue S. Andrewes Church in Holburne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1596.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures B²  ² B-C⁴ D² .</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The necessitie, and excellencie of archerie.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Archery --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16807:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16807:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ABRIEFE TREATISE, To prooue the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie and excellence of the VSE OF ARCHERIE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſtracted out of ancient and Moderne</hi> Writers. By R: S.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peruſed, and allowed by Aucthoritie.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <p>HEB DDIM HEB DDIEV</p>
            </figure>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by <hi>Richard Iohnes,</hi> at the Roſe and Crowne; next <hi>aboue</hi> S. Andrewes <hi>Church in</hi> Holburne. 1596.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16807:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16807:2"/>
            <head>To the Nobilitie and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TLEMEN OF ENGLANDE: <hi>The Companies of</hi> Bowyers <hi>and</hi> Fletchers <hi>wiſh encreaſe of Honour, continuall health and all happineſſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ay it pleaſe your good Lordſhips, &amp; the wor thie minded Gentlemen of England, in all humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie to giue vs leaue to remember you of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent honor, whereby many forrein Nations, but eſpe ciallie this Realme of England, hath benlong hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den famous for victories atchieued, vnder the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>duct of their right prudent &amp; valiant Princes &amp; Captaines, by the wonderful effect of Archerie: &amp; to deplore vnto your honors and wiſdoms, the diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance, yea (almoſt) the vtter extirpation ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, within this Realm: And withal, our own miſerable eſtates, who with many other poore Artificers that haue had their maintenance therby, are (in great nomber) brought to vtter ruyn and decaie. In the rowme wherof, is crept in the noyſome vſe of vnthriftie &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Games: Wherfore, to ſtirre vp in your honors and worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, a due commiſſeration of theſe great miſchiefes, we haue cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed this Abſtract to be taken out of former Writers, and from right credible and true Reportes: Not intending heereby to inſinuate to our ſelues any ſuch fauour or reliefe within this Common-wealth, for our priuate auaile, as to innouate any ſupperfluous thing, or to driue the ſame to any charge at al, vnleſſe the quallytie of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect whereof we intreat, ſhal in your graue diſcreſcions be adiudged to be worthie therof, more for the honor &amp; ſauegard of her Royall Maieſtie, her knigdoms and dominions, then for our priuat regard.</p>
            <p>For if (in your iudgements) the Examples and Reaſons in this Briefe contained, ſhal not be holden of waight and momentwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie the preferment of Archetie, then ſhal we be pleaſed rather to ſincke in our owne miſeries, then to become vnprofitablie burthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous to our Prince and Countrey.</p>
            <p>And therfore, do wee (humblie) intreate, that we maie bee with ſauour, permitted to propoſe the ſame, to your Honours and Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes: to th'ende, that if they ſhall ſeeme forcible, and worthie
<pb facs="tcp:16807:3"/> your conſiderations, it wold then pleaſe you with a fauorable zeale to further thoſe proceedings her Royall Maieſtie, hath and ſhall take for our reliefe herein, which is, that by your good endeuours, her Maieſties forward Subiects in the exerciſe of Archerie, maie be cheriſhed, &amp; obſtinat perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s refuſing to be reformed (diſpoſing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues rather to practiſe vnlawfull Games) may be chaſtned &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected according to the forme of the laudable lawes in that behalfe made &amp; prouided: nor is it our meaning, to derogate from the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of the vſe or excellence of any other ſtrong or approoued weapons fit for the wars, be they of fire or others, ſuch as your wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes &amp; counſelles haue prouided to be had &amp; ordained: but that both (not compared togither, whither ſhould in all reſpects be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the other, but ſo ioyned together, that the one ſhould bee an aide &amp; helpe for the other) might ſo ſtrengthen the Realme on al ſides in their ſeuerall natures, that not any Nation may become dangerous vnto vs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor we diſarme ourſelues of that weapon wher in God &amp; Nature hath made vs excell, and whereby we haue euer ben preualent ouer al our enemies: For by the Supplie to be made by Archrie amongſt the greateſt nomber of perſons (which if any preſent need ſhuld require, could not be furniſhed with other war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like munition, both for want of abilitie, &amp; alſo by reaſon it can not wel be had for ſo many as ther be able men to ſerue with the ſame) it wil fal out, that noe fit perſons will be founde naked or vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table be the accidentes of Warre neuer ſo ſuddaine: Of the want wherof, we haue heard men of good Iudgement latelie complaine, in reſpect of the late petie incurſion made by the Enemie vpon the Sea-coaſt in the Countie of CORNWAL: Wherfore, it may pleaſe your Honours and Wiſdomes to accept of our good intents (though we be of the meaneſt ſort of her Highneſſe Subiects) who do not ſo much herein pretend our owne prefermentes or aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, as the aduauncement of the Honour of this Realme, whiche hath ſhoane bright in your noble Aunceſtors, by their manifould Conqueſtes, famouſlie atchieued, eſpeciallie, by vertue of this Weapon: And we ſhall (deuotely) praie to God, that that Fame and Honour may redouble vpon your ſelues &amp; yours, in this time of her Maieſties moſt happie raigne, and ſo ſucceſſiuelie, for euer.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:16807:3"/>
            <head>Certen Collections out of ancient and Moderne Writers, proouing the necesſitie and excellence of the vſe of Archerie:</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deuided into three partes, vz.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>I. That the vſe of Archerie is a moſt auncient and noble Exerciſe: And that for Princes and great men, it is a moſt faire and honourable Practiſe.</item>
                  <item>II. That it is moſt neceſſarie for the Subiects to vſe the ſame both in peace and warre.</item>
                  <item>III. And for Battelles and victories in the field (whervpon our Nation void of ſtrong Townes doth ſpeciallie repoſe it ſelfe) Archerie to be of farre greater effect then anie other weapon that euer was inuented: And that in reſpect therof onclie, this Realme of England hath been euer feared and honored of all Nations.</item>
               </list>
            </argument>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>The first Part.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>LATO, Calimachus</hi> and <hi>Galene,</hi> very noble writers bring the inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſhooting from <hi>Apollo:</hi> for the which cauſe, Shooting is highly praiſed of
<hi>Galen</hi> in his booke of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to good Artes, where hee
<pb facs="tcp:16807:4"/> ſaith, that meane craftes be firſt ſonnde out by men or beaſtes, as weauing by a Spyder, &amp;c. But high and commendable Sciences by Goddes, as Shoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and Muſicke by
<hi>Apollo.</hi> And if wee ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue <hi>Nicholas de Lyra, Lamech</hi> killed
<hi>Caine</hi> with a Shaſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cyaxares</hi> the king of the <hi>Medes,</hi> and great grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father to <hi>Cyrus,</hi> kept a ſort of <hi>Scythians</hi> with him on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for this purpoſe, to teach his ſon
<hi>Aſtiages</hi> to ſhoot.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cyrus</hi> being a child, was brought vp in ſhooting, which <hi>Xenephon</hi> wold neuer haue made me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion of, except it had been fit for Princes to haue vſed, ſeeing that
<hi>Xenephon</hi> wrote <hi>Cyrus</hi> life (as <hi>Tullie</hi> ſayth) not to ſhewe what
<hi>Cyrus</hi> did, but what all manner of Princes both in paſtimes &amp; earneſt matters ought to doe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Darius</hi> the firſt king of <hi>Perſia</hi> of that name, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed playnlie, how fit it is for a king to loue and vſe Shooting, who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded this ſentence to be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten on his tombe for a princely memory and praiſe.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Darius the King lyeth buried heere,</l>
                  <l>That in Shooting and riding had no peere.</l> 
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Herodian</hi> his opinion of <hi>Commodus</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, was: that he had no Princely thing in him, but ſtrength of bodie, and good Shooting.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Themiſtius</hi> the noble Philoſopher, in an Oration made to <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Emperour, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendeth him for three things that hee vſed of a Childe: Shooting: Riding of a horſe well, and feates of Armes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16807:4"/>It is moſt manifeſt in the hiſtories of our Nation, that the kings and Princes of this Realm haue bin excellent Archers: And this age can witneſſe with what loue and affection the right noble kings of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous memorie, king <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight, and <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt, did vſe and exerciſe the ſame in their owne perſons.</p>
               <p>By Shooting is the minde honorably exerciſed, where a man alwaies deſireth to bee beſt (which is a word of honor) and that by the ſame way that ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue it ſelf doth, coueting to come nigheſt a moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect end, or meane ſtanding between two extreams, eſchuing
<hi>ſhort</hi> or <hi>gone,</hi> or on eyther ſide, <hi>wide.</hi> For which cauſes
<hi>Ariſtotle</hi> himſelfe ſaith: that Shooting and Vertue be very like. And that of all other, it is<note place="margin">Ariſtotle de Morib.</note> the moſt honeſt paſtime, and leaſt occaſion to naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe, two things doe very plainly prooue: <hi>vz Day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light</hi> and <hi>Open place.</hi> If Shooting fault at any time, it hides not it ſelfe, but openly accuſeth and bewrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it ſelfe: which is the next way to amendement, as wiſe men doe ſay.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>THE SECOND PART.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ot only kinges and Emperors haue beene brought vp in ſhooting, but alſo the beſt common Wealths that euer were haue made goodly actes &amp; laws for it: as the <hi>Perſians</hi> (who vnder <hi>Cyrus</hi> conquered very many nations) had a law, that their children ſhould learne three thinges only, from fiue yeares old to twenty: To ride a horſe wel, to ſhoot wel, &amp; to ſpeak trueth alwaies and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer lie.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16807:5"/>The <hi>Romans</hi> (as <hi>Leo</hi> the Emperour in his booke of the ſleightes of warre telleth) had a law that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man ſhuld vſe Shooting in time of peace, while he were fourty yeeres olde: And that euerie houſe ſhould haue a Bowe and fourty Shaftes ready for all needes: The omitting of which Law (ſaith <hi>Leo</hi>) among the youth, hath beene the only occaſion, why the <hi>Romaines</hi> loſt a great deale of their Empire.</p>
               <p>The firſte Statute and Lawe that euer <hi>Dauid</hi> made after he was King, was this: that all the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſraell</hi> ſhoulde learne to ſhoote (according to a Law made many a day before that time, for the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out of Shooting) as it is written (ſaith Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture)
<hi>in libro Iuſtorum,</hi> which booke we haue not now<note place="margin">Reg, 2, 1</note> extant.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plato</hi> wold haue common Maſters and ſtipends<note place="margin">De Leg 7</note> for to teach youth to ſhoot: And for the ſame purpoſe he would haue broad fields neere euery Citie made common for men to vſe ſhooting in.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leo</hi> the Emperour in his ſixt booke: Let all the youth of <hi>Rome</hi> bee compelled to vſe ſhooting, either more or leſſe: And alwayes to beare their bow and their quyuer about them, vntill they be fourty years old: For ſince Shooting was neglected and decayed among the <hi>Romanes,</hi> many a Battell and fielde hath been loſt.</p>
               <p>Againe, in the xi. Book and 50. Chap. Let your Souldiers haue their weapons wel appointed and trimmed, but aboue all other thinges regarde moſt ſhooting: And therfore, let men when ther is no war vſe Shooting at home: For the leauing off onely of
<pb facs="tcp:16807:5"/> Shooting hath brought ruine &amp; decay to the whole<note place="margin">Ruin &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caie to the whole Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire by lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing off of Shooting.</note> Empire of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After wardes hee commandeth againe his Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines by theſe wordes: Arme your hoaſt as I haue appointed you, but eſpecially with Bowe and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows plenty: For ſhooting is a thing of much might &amp; power in warre, and chiefly againſt the <hi>Saracens</hi> &amp; <hi>Turks,</hi> which people haue all their hope of victorie in their Bowe and Shafts.</p>
               <p>Beſides all this, in another place hee writeth thus to his Captaine. <hi>Artillerie</hi> is eaſie to bee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, and in time of great neede a thing moſt profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. Therefore wee ſtraightly commaund you to make Proclamation to all men vnder our domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, either in warre or peace, to all Citties, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughes and Townes, and finallye to all manner of men: that euery ſeuerall pearſon haue bowe and ſhaftes of his owne: And euery houſe beſides this, to haue a ſtanding bearing Bow and fourty ſhafts for all needes: And that they exerciſe themſelues in holtes, hilles and dales, playnes and woods, for all maner of chaunces in warre.</p>
               <p>And yet Shooting (although they ſett neuer ſo much by it) was neuer ſo good (then) as it is now in <hi>England:</hi> which thing to be true, is verie pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>table, in that <hi>Leo</hi> doth ſay: That he would haue his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers take off their Arrowe-heads, and one ſhoot at another for their exerciſe: Which play if the Engliſh Archers vſed, I thinke they would find ſmall ſport, and leſſe pleaſure in it. But the exerciſe therof other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, bringeth a notable aduantage to them that
<pb facs="tcp:16807:6"/> doe practiſe the ſame: For experience doth teach vs, that the ſtrongeſt men doe not alwayes make the ſtrongeſt ſhoote, which thing prooueth that drawe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing ſtrong lyeth not ſo much in the ſtrength of man, as in the vſe of Shooting.</p>
               <p>To conclude this ſecond part, if a man ſhuld per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe all paſtimes and exerciſes profitable to be ſet by of euery man, woorthy to be rebuked of no man, fit for all ages, perſons and places, and a medicine to purge the whole land of all peſtilent gaming, onelie Shooting ſhall appeare, wherein all theſe commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities ſhal be found, being ſtrengthened by putting in execution ſuch laudable actes &amp; ſtatutes as haue bin on that behalfe made and prouided by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments of this Realme.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>THE THIRD PART.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Vripides</hi> (euery of whoſe verſes <hi>Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie</hi> thinketh to be an Aucthoritie) doth ſay, That of all weapons the beſt is, where with leaſt danger of our ſelfe, we may hurt our enemie moſt: And that is (as may bee ſuppoſed) Artille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: which now adayes is taken for two thinges, Gunnes and Bowes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peter Nannius</hi> a learned man of <hi>Louain,</hi> in a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue ſheweth exceeding commodities of both: And ſome diſcommodities of Gunnes: as infinit coſt and charge, cumberſom cariage if they be great, the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain leuelling, the peril of them that ſtand by, &amp;c.
<pb facs="tcp:16807:6"/> Beſides al this, contrary wind and weather, which hindereth them not a little, and ſometime maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnprofitable: yet of ſhooting he cannot reherſe one diſcommoditie.</p>
               <p>But becauſe ſome ſort of men at Armes would bring our Magiſtrates and the better ſorte of our people and nation to miſlike this ancient weapon, as vnprofitable for the wars of our dayes: &amp; wold attribute alexcellence to the Muſquet and Caliuer: See Sir <hi>Iohn Smyth,</hi> Knight, in his booke treating of Archery from fol. 20, to fol. 28. wher you may find he vtterly conſuteth them, proouing three eſpeciall poyntes againſt them, vz.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 Archers to be moſt ready in the field.</item>
                  <item>2 Archers to faile leaſt in ſhooting.</item>
                  <item>3 And that they doe anney the Enemies moſt, be they horſemen or footmen.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And then after many vnreplyable reaſons, offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that hee will neuer refuſe with 8000. good Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers to aduenture his life againſt 20000. of the beſt ſhot in Chriſtendom.</p>
               <p>Where <hi>fol. 23. 27. 28.</hi> he prooueth long Bowes to be moſt excellent for battailes and great encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, both againſt horſemen and footmen, for that it is a ready weapon both in faire and foule weather which ſhot is not: &amp; that the arrowes in flying both in their deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; fal, kil &amp; wound from the face to the foot, into many ranks of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aduers battel or ſquadro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:16807:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> Which the ſhot doth not, but in their point blancke (ſtaying at the firſt, ſecond, or third ranke of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie) nor then, but ſeldom by reaſon of many imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, which hee ſetteth downe there. Where it is further to bee noted, that very many ranks of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers may (with couenience) altogether, one behind another, ſhoot into the Enemies battell, which the gunnes cannot doe by reaſon of their point blanck, whereby they muſt needs endanger their fellowes before them: So that in <hi>fol. 29.</hi> hee concludeth, (as wel he may) that ther is no doubt, but Archers with their vollees of Arrowes, will wound, kill, and hurt aboue an hundred men and horſes, for euery one ſo to be done by the ſhot.</p>
               <p>In <hi>fol. 18. 19.</hi> He (hauing ſhewed many imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons belongyng to the Shot) auerreth, that for thoſe cauſes in many great encounters verie hot, and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinued many howers with Shot, with new Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies on both ſides, within three, foure or fiue ſkores and neerer, there hath not been ſlaine and hurt on both ſides with Bullettes thirtie men. And therfore in
<hi>fol. 28.</hi> he ſaith: that it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to paſſe, that when men and horſe haue ben in three or foure ſkirmiſhes and do ſee that they receiue no hurt, neither by fier, or ſmoke, nor noiſe: nor that in many thouſandes of men there are not twentie men ſlain, nor hurt, they grow after to be tar leſſe in doubt therof.</p>
               <p>Howbeit the vollees of Arrows flying together in the aire as thick as haile doe not only terrifie and amaze, in moſt terrible ſort, the ears, eies, and harts both of horſes and men, with the noiſe and ſight of
<pb facs="tcp:16807:7"/> their comming: But they alſo in their diſcents, doe not leaue in a whole ſquadron of horſemen or foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men (although they bee in motion) ſo much as one man or horſe vnſtricken and wounded with diuers Arrowes, if the number of Archers be anſwerable to the number of the ſquadron.<note place="margin">
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>Downward-pointing arrow</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides all which, it is to be noted, that horſes in the fielde being wounded, or but lightly hurt with Arrowes, they through the great paine, that vppon euery motion they doe feel in their fleſh, vaines, and ſinewes, by the ſhaking of the Arrowes with their barbed heads hanging in them, doe preſently fall a yerking and leaping, as if they were madde, in ſuch ſort, as be it ſquadron, or in troope, they doe quite diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order one another, and neuer leaue vntill they haue throwne and caſt their maiſters. Wheras contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, Horſes that are in vitall parts hurt with Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, or the bones of their legs, ſhoulders or backes be broken, they doe preſently fall downe: Or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, although they bee ſtricken cleane through, or that the Bullets do ſtill remaine in them, they after the firſt ſhrinke, at the entring of the Bullet, do paſſe their carier as though they had very litle or no hurt. In which Treatiſe
<hi>fol. 26. 27.</hi> hee complaineth of all ſortes of Magiſtrates, for that they doe not ſee thoſe notable Lawes made by former kinges for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Archerie to bee put in execution, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto people of this realm (of a ſingular gift of God) by a naturall inclination, come to be perfect and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent: Whereby wee are ſuffered to diſcontinue a weapon euer terrible to the enemies, and whereof
<pb facs="tcp:16807:8"/> they neuer had ſkill: and vpon any ſudden ſhall bee enforced to ſight with them at their owne weapons wherein (by neceſſity) they are continually trained vp, we being therin vnpractiſed.</p>
               <p>The ſame knight, in the Proeme of his booke prooueth that the <hi>Egyptians</hi> did firſt conquer a great parte of <hi>Aſia, Europe,</hi> and <hi>Affricke</hi> by their Armie, which did conſiſt moſt of Archerie: But they falling into ſecurity and drunkennes, and neglect of that weapon, were conquered by <hi>Alexander</hi> the greate, the greateſt part of whoſe Armie did conſiſt of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherie.</p>
               <p>In like ſort, and with the like weapon were the <hi>Grecians</hi> conquered with the
<hi>Arabians.</hi> After the ſame Diſcipline of Archery they reuiued. And after (vpon neglect thereof) againe conquered and quite ouerthrowne by <hi>Mahomet</hi> with his <hi>Turkes</hi> and
<hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſaries</hi> that conſiſted moſt of Bow-men.</p>
               <p>King <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Ioſiah</hi> performed great effectes, therewith: By this weapon God gaue many victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to the Iewes: and by the ſame for their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion<note place="margin">Pſa. 7. 63. 75</note> they receiued diuers ouerthrowes of the Gentiles. Beſides that, king <hi>Dauid</hi> doth cal Bowes a mighty power, and in his Pſalmes the veſſels of death.</p>
               <p>God when hee promiſeth help to the Iewes, hee vſeth no kind of ſpeaking ſo much as this: That hee<note place="margin">Deut. 32.</note> will bend his Bowe, and die his Shaftes in Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles blood: Whereby it is manifeſt, that Shooting is a wooderfull thing in warre, whereunto the high power of God is likened.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16807:8"/>When <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> the valiant Captaine ſlue and tooke Priſoners, all the
<hi>Lacedemonians</hi> beſides of the Citie of <hi>Pilos,</hi> the Shaftes went ſo thick that day (ſayth <hi>Thucydides)</hi> that no man could ſee their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. I <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> taken Priſoner, was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of one of <hi>Athens,</hi> whether they were ſtout Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes that were ſlaine or no of the <hi>Lacedemonians:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Thucid. 4.</note> He anſwered nothing els but this: Make much of thoſe Shaftes of yours, for they know neither ſtout nor vnſtout. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Gothes. Vandals, Alans,</hi> and other Northren Nations, inuaded and conquered
<hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Greece</hi> and beſieged <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> ſpoyled <hi>Hungarie, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria, Illiria;</hi> and <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> waſted all <hi>Italie,</hi> ſacked
<hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> inuaded <hi>Affrick,</hi> &amp;c. And it is moſt euident they atchieued all theſe victories, more with the effect of Bowes, then with all the reſt of their weapons.</p>
               <p>With the like weapon did the <hi>Arrabians</hi> inuade <hi>Conſtantinople, Meſopotamia, Surria, Armenia</hi> &amp; <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia, Ieruſalem, Egypt, Barbarie, &amp;c.</hi> They diſcontinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this weapon, were by the ſame chiefly conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Turkes.</p>
               <p>The like did the <hi>Tartars</hi> againſt <hi>Parthia, Media, Armenia, Meſopotamia</hi> and
<hi>Surria,</hi> with innumerable numbers of Archers on horſback.</p>
               <p>So did <hi>Tamberlaine</hi> the Tartar Emperour, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw <hi>Baiazeth</hi> the Turkiſh Emperor, by reaſon his Armie did farre exceed the Turks in the number of Archers.</p>
               <p>Which moſt excellent effects of Archery, was the
<pb facs="tcp:16807:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> cauſe that <hi>Amurath</hi> the ſecond Emperor of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
                  <hi>Turks,</hi> did within few yeares after inſtitute for the guard of his perſon, a number of <hi>Ianiſſaries</hi> on foot (beeing Chriſtians renyed) taught from their youth to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe the Bowe: And ſo of the Harquebuze: So that when the
<hi>Turke</hi> ſendeth any his <hi>Baſlaes</hi> to beſiege a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny towns, they all vſe to take with them both their bowes and Harquebuzes: their Harquebuzes to vſe in trenches againſt places fortifyed: &amp; their bowes for ſeruices of the field: But the <hi>Turke</hi> for guarde of his perſon, and for al battels and great encounters in the field, doeth euer prefer the Bowes before the Harquebuzes, <hi>fol. 41<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 42.</hi> So likewiſe doe the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, Perſians,</hi> and <hi>Parthians</hi> vnder the <hi>Sophie:</hi> who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they haue had the vſe of ſhot long before vs in <hi>Europe,</hi> yet haue they, and do ſtill prefer their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and Bowes for Battels and Victories before their weapons of fire. <hi>fol. 42</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is very certain, that ſhooting is the chief thing wherewith God ſuffereth the Turke to puniſh our ſinnes withall: The youth there is brought vp in<note place="margin">Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Turc,</note> Shooting: and it is well knowne to the <hi>Spaniardes</hi> the might of their ſhooting, who in the towne called
<hi>Newcaſtle</hi> in <hi>Illerica,</hi> were all ſlaine by the Turkes Arrowes, when the
<hi>Spaniardes</hi> had no vſe of their gunnes by reaſon of the raine.</p>
               <p>And ſince that, the Emperours Maieſtie himſelfe at the Citty of <hi>Argier</hi> in
<hi>Affricke,</hi> had his hoaſt ſore handled with the <hi>Turkes</hi> Arrowes, when his guns ſtood him in no ſeruice at all by the like accident of raine.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16807:9"/>And therfore, as concerning all theſe kingdoms<note place="margin">Plin, lib, 16 Chap.
36</note> and common wealths, I may conclude with <hi>Plinie,</hi> thus: If any man would remember the <hi>Ethiopians, Egyptians, Arabians,</hi> the men of <hi>Indie,</hi> of <hi>Scythia,</hi> ſo manie people in the Eaſt of the <hi>Samaritanes,</hi> and all the kingdome of the
<hi>Parthians,</hi> &amp;c. hee ſhall perceiue halfe the part of the world to liue in ſubiection, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by the might and power of Shooting.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Proofes from our Nation of former and moderne times.</head>
               <p>THe ſayd Sir <hi>Iohn Smyth,</hi> knight, <hi>fol. 29. 30. 31.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tilburie Campe.</note> proouing that by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> example of placing Bowes in the Armie at <hi>Tilburie. An. Dom.
1588.</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of this age in general, not to be expert in that Diſcipline, hee teacheth the order of our Aunceſtors therein, in this ſort. <hi>vz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They placed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the face of the men at Armes of <hi>France</hi> and other Nations (who were then better armed then now wee vſe to bee) and the effect was ſuch, that flying in the ayre as thicke as ſnow, with a terrible noiſe (much like a tempeſtious wind) they did leaue no diſarmed place of horſe, or man vnſtric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and vnwounded, as may well appeare by the battell of <hi>Creſſey;</hi> that king <hi>Edward</hi> the thirde, and his ſonne Prince <hi>Edw.</hi> won againſt <hi>Philip of France,</hi> where the <hi>French</hi> were ſix to one wel armed: where were ſlain xi. Princes, a thouſand and two hundred knightes, and thirty thouſand Souldiours: The
<pb facs="tcp:16807:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> woonderfull effectes and terrour of the ſhotte of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes was that day ſuch, as neither men at armes nor other Horſmen of diuers Nations, were able to enter and breake the Archers, being without pikes ſtakes, bankes, and trenches to guard them, but in the plaine Fieldes: The Archers with their Vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lees of Arrowes did break the ranks both of Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and footmen, wounding and killing both horſe and man, the French kings horſe being ſlain vnder him, and himſelfe in perill.</p>
               <p>The like or greater ouerthrow was acted by the ſame Prince, againſt <hi>Iohn</hi> king of
<hi>France</hi> in the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell of <hi>Poicters,</hi> with ſix thouſand Archers, and two thouſand armed men againſt 60000. French.</p>
               <p>The ſame Prince fought the like battell in <hi>Spain</hi> ouerthrew a hundred thouſand men in one battel by the wonderful effect of Archers.</p>
               <p>So was the battell of <hi>Herringes</hi> fought there in <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſixt his time, and won by Archery,</p>
               <p>In the ſame kings time (as the French Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles do report) the L. of <hi>Belay</hi> acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panied with two hundred French Lances going to <hi>Mans,</hi> met with an Engliſh Captain called <hi>Berrie,</hi> and with him 80. Archers, by whom the Lances were ouerthrowne, and diuers taken priſoners.</p>
               <p>The like encounter happened about that time, between <hi>Guyan de Coing,</hi> a French Captaine with 120. Lances, and Sir <hi>William Olde</hi> with twentye Archers, with like ſucceſſe.</p>
               <p>But for that it may be obiected: That it may bee graunted, that Archery was a preualent weapon
<pb facs="tcp:16807:10"/> in auncient times before the Muſquet and Calliuer came to the perfection of their vſe: It is not amiſſe to produce later inſtances of theſe our ages.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Seruices of great effect done by Archerie of our Nation in theſe our times.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Otable ſeruice was done in the time of king <hi>Henrie</hi> the 8. of famous me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie (vpon a conuoy between <hi>Guiens</hi> and <hi>Teroun)</hi> by Archers.</p>
               <p>In the time of king <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt, 1548. <hi>Ket</hi> with his <hi>Norfolke</hi> Rebels, by one conflict and a foughten field (beeing men vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed) did great exploits againſt the Duke of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland</hi> by Archers: So that the Duke loſt his good opinion of Harquebuzies, and would euer after ſay publikely, the Bow to be the nobleſt weapon of the world: This Sir <hi>Iohn Smyth</hi> ſetteth down from the certaine reporte of the late Earle of Warwicke, who was there preſent.</p>
               <p>In the ſame kinges time the Weſterne Rebels<note place="margin">The right honorable the Lord of Hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ldon, L, Chamber laine that now is, an eie-witnes.</note> droue the Spaniſh and Italian Harquebuzies from all their ſtrengths with vollees of Arrowes, which ſir <hi>Iohn Smyth</hi> alſo hath hard the L. Chamberlaine that now is very notably report (who was there an eie witnes) Captaine <hi>Spinola</hi> an Italian, a verie braue Souldiour, and wounded with Arrowes in theſe ſeruices, gaue ſingular commendation of the Archerie of England.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16807:11"/>The Battell of <hi>Floddon</hi> hill, where <hi>Iames</hi> king Scottes was ſlain, is very famous: where the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of <hi>Cheſhire</hi> and <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> got immortal name and praiſe for euer.</p>
               <p>The feare onely of Engliſh Archers hath done ſtranger things then is read of els where: and that not long ſithence, betwixt <hi>Eske</hi> and <hi>Leuen</hi> at <hi>Sandie Sikes</hi> did appear, where the whole nobility of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> for feare of the Archers of
<hi>England,</hi> were drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and taken Priſoners.</p>
               <p>There is an olde prouerbe in <hi>Scotland,</hi> that euery Engliſh Archer beareth vnder his girdle twenty foure Scottes.</p>
               <p>And if it bee true, as it is ſayd, when the king of <hi>England</hi> hath been in
<hi>France,</hi> the Prieſtes at home (becauſe they were Archers) haue been able to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow all <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Biſhop <hi>Latimer</hi> in his ſixt Sermon made before<note place="margin">Biſhop La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timer his commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Archerie.</note> king <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt, deſired the Lordes, as they lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the honour and glory of God, and as they inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to remooue his indignation, to prouide for the practiſe of Shooting: which hee called the gift of god, wherby we excelled all other Nations: and an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument wherby he hath giuen vnto vs many vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories.</p>
               <p>The foreſaide Lord <hi>Warwicke</hi> did alſo reporte, that when he was Lieutenant generall at <hi>Newha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,</hi> hee did ſend to the Admirall of <hi>France,</hi> then fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by her Maieſty, ſix hundred harquebuziers, who thankfully receiuing them, yet ſaid, hee had rather haue had two hundred Archers: And that he would
<pb facs="tcp:16807:11"/> with them performe greater ſeruice: This meſſage was brought from the Admiral by Sir <hi>Francis Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſet,</hi> Sir <hi>Richard Throgmorton,</hi> and Sir <hi>William Pellam,</hi> knightes.</p>
               <p>Woonderful ſeruice was ſithence done by foure ſcore of our Archers, againſt Dutch &amp; French Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huſiers in <hi>France,</hi> to the great admiration of the <hi>Reingraue:</hi> whereupon hee did proteſt and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the Long-bowes of England to bee the beſt weapons for the field that were vſed by any nation of Chriſtendome: And ſaid that the Queene of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land had great cauſe ſo to eſteem of them. Reported by the ſaid Earle of
<hi>Warwicke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Iames Croft</hi> declared many notable ſeruices hee had ſeene done by Archers in
<hi>England, Fraunce, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About <hi>Bartholmew</hi> tyde laſt, 1595. there came out of <hi>Scotland,</hi> one <hi>Iames Forgeſon,</hi> Bowyer to the king of Scots, who credibly reported, that about two<note place="margin">Scots be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers.</note> yeares paſt, certaine rebelles did riſe there againſt the king, who ſent againſt them fiue hundred horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men well appointed: They meeting three hundred of the Rebels Bowmen, encountred each with other, where the Bowe-men ſlue two hundred and foure ſcore of their horſes, and killed, wounded, and ſore<note place="margin">Scots make prouiſion of Archerie</note> hurt moſt part of the kinges men. Whereupon the ſaid <hi>Forgeſon</hi> was ſent hether from the king with Commiſſion to buy vp ten thouſande Bowes and Bowſtaues: But becauſe he could not ſpeed heer, he went ouer into the Eaſt countries for them: This report wil bee prooued by credible perſons of the cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of London.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16807:12"/>It may therefore bee well concluded with Sir <hi>Iohn Smyth:</hi> That all conquering Nations haue made chiefe choiſe of the Bowes, as of the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent kind of weapon for victories and conqueſts.</p>
               <p>And yet (as he ſayth) it is euident by al hiſtories and all ſuch as haue trauelled many partes of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope, Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Affricke,</hi> that Engliſh Bowes &amp; Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes doe exceede and excell all others vſed by all forein Nations, not only in ſubſtance and ſtrength but alſo in length and bigneſſe.</p>
               <p>Neither is it vnknowne, that the French Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and Gentlemen of this age, attribute all the former victories of the Engliſh againſt themſelues, and their Aunceſtors, more to the effect of Archers, then to any extraordinary valiancie of our nation.</p>
               <p>It therfore were great pittie (or rather impiety) to ſuffer this noble ancient weapon (being ſo migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie a ſtrength and honor to al nations that haue and doe vſe the ſame, and eſpecially to our Engliſh peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple aboue all others, for the reaſons and examples aboue rehearſed) to goe to decay amongſt vs, while there is godly lawes prouided for the ſame, and while it may be vſed of any perſon, and the ſame perſon fully prouided of Bowe and arrowes for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe (according to the preſcription of the lawe on that behalfe) vnder twentie pence. The practiſe wherof (beſides his own excellence) wil greatly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh the noyſome and peſtilent cuſtom of vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full games now crept in vſe in the roome therof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing far more chargeable then Archery is.</p>
               <p>But there is great hope that this honorable wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon
<pb facs="tcp:16807:12"/> now (by vſe of vnlawful games) greatly decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, will reſume to it ſelfe within this realme, his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ſtrength and vertue (and that in ſhort time, the people of a naturall inclination being giuen there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto) ſeeing it hath pleaſed her royal Maieſty, vnder her Highneſſe hand, to haue giuen out warrant vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the right Honorable Sir <hi>Iohn Puckering</hi> knight, Lord keeper of the great Seale of <hi>England,</hi> to grant out Commiſſions vnder the ſame Seale, to put in execution one laudable Statute, made in the time of her right Princely Father for exerciſe of Archery, and debarring of vnlawful games: And ſeeing that the Lordes of her Highneſſe priuy Counſell haue alſo by their Letters directted to his Lordſh. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended the ſame, as an Act fit to bee performed for the honor and ſtrength of the Realme.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
